Guide to the Cuban Revolution Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Andrew St. George Photographs, Films, and Papers, 1957-1960; Series I
  - Photographs
    - Contact Book II
      - Book II Print 33: Fidel Castro being interviewed, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 103)
        Fidel Castro at La Plata headquarters in early fall of 1958 giving TV sound interview to CBC cameraman Erik Durschmied. Some of the frames (16, 29) show Fidel consulting his (English-language) notes during interview; most of the other frames show him delivering answers (at) invisible TV camera. See also Print 32.
      - Book II Print 34: Activities along approach to Fidel Castro's headquarters, undated (Box 2, Folder 104)
        This sheet was photographed along the approach route to Fidel Castro's headquarters near La Plata. Lt. Vilo Acuna testing his homemade rebel rifle grenade launcher (frames 3-10; See also Print 18.). Frames 12-18: Rebel requisitioned road grader with its proud guerrilla crew. Among approach routes to central guerrilla areas - the approach routes through foothills - growing rebel troop units were beginning to maintain roads, transfer points, supply dumps for gasoline and lubricants, and other semi-permanent installations designed to insure a predictable flow of military traffic through back roads of rebel zone. Frames 25-26 show Capt. Mario Hidalgo with his family. On right, youth in uniform is Mario's son, Hanibal Hidalgo, then photographer's travel aide. Note dog-tag hanging from Hanibal's neck: it was captured from government soldiers and laboriously re-engraved by hand, giving Hanibal much-wanted military appearance. Frames 32-37: Outside Fidel's headquarters hut at La Plata, the headquarters' dental officer, Dr. Enrique Borges, has his foot-operated drill and consulta.
      - Book II Print 35: Rebel bomb shop and Fidel Castro's headquarters, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 105)
        Frames 25-28 show Cdte. Luis "El Guajiro" Crespo at his bomb shop (see also Prints 14 and 15.) Frames 17-20: Celia Sanchez. Frames 9-14: This is Fidel Castro's place of work in headquarters hut where he had only desk ever used by Fidel during two-year insurgency. Three framed photos overhead show his son, Fidelito. Frame 16: Orlando Pupo, jefe de escolta. Frames 23-24 show two important adjuncts to headquarters life: supply and equipment bearers. These men are bringing electrical gear used to repair radio gear and fuse homemade bombs. Frames 5-8: one of the items manufactured from electrical supplies brought in by runners is this little cheeseglass-detonator known as "Che's jam jar," either because Che invented it or because it was developed at bomb shop in Che's column. It is an impact-squeeze detonator that will activate a concealed road mine or a large hand-hurled bomb.
      - Book II Print 36: Rebel column, undated (Box 2, Folder 106)
        Rebel column on the march toward area surrounding Santiago.
      - Book II Print 37: Andrew St. George; Hanibal Hidalgo; Victor Boronat, undated (Box 2, Folder 107)
        Andrew St. George at wayside halt while on the march among rebel outposts in the vicinity of Puerto Boniato. Photographer's travel aide, Lt. Hanibal Hidalgo, is shown on frames 27-30. Rebel organizer Victor Boronat is shown playing guitar on frames 2-3.
      - Book II Print 38: Rebel platoon above El Cobre sanctuary; interrogation of suspect, undated (Box 2, Folder 108)
        Rebel platoon on march among heights controlling the carretera nacional above El Cobre sanctuary (frames 5-8). Unit commander Capt. Rigoberto Ramirez is shown in center of frame 14 (long beard, field cap, cartridge belt). Suspicious wayfarer, intercepted earlier by rebel platoon and interrogated to no avail, is threatened by execution (frames 12-13). Suspect falls in fright when rifle is fired over his head, and Capt. Ramirez menaces him with pistol, firing past his ear. But suspect was not otherwise harmed and released later same day. The threat of summary execution was rebel's only means of coercing information from suspects.
      - Book II Print 39: Rebel patrols combing approach to Siboney, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 109)
        Rebel patrols combing approach area to Siboney, overlooking Santiago. Column commander Cdte. Rene de los Santos is shown in frames 22-23: smiling officer in center. When these pictures were taken, the landscape was of key significance, for it indicated decisive rebel breakthrough towards Santiago in early fall of 1958.
      - Book II Print 40: Rebel advances, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 110)
        These shots were made in the early fall of 1958 to document astonishing rebel advances, and government military withdrawals. A guerrilla patrol is shown here playing jukebox at road-side halt on the march above Puerto Boniato. For Fidel's faithful, junglebound for eighteen months, these were miraculous portents of the unmistakably approaching victory over the tottering Batista forces.
      - Book II Print 41: Interrogation of suspect; Rebel troop military encounter. For glossary of mock execution shown here on top frames, see also Print 38, undated (Box 2, Folder 111)
        Interrogation of suspect (see also Print 38). Capt. Rigoberto Ramirez's rebel troop unit on the march above El Cobre. They come under fire from medium mortar, apparently fired by government unit stationed downhill near El Cobre: phosphorus shells ignite savannah and patrol dashes for cover.
      - Book II Print 42: Rebel attack on El Cobre, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 112)
        These frames show a small-unit, fast-moving rebel attack on El Cobre. Frames 4-13: Capt. Rigoberto Ramirez sights target down in valley at nightfall. Note white towers of El Cobre sanctuary, famous Cuban landmark, visible in distance. Frames 14-15 show rebel soldiers hastily requisitioning supplies in tiny Chinese grocery on El Cobre's outskirts. Rest of frames show Ramirez's patrol attacking and burning attack target: army supply dump outside El Cobre.
      - Book II Print 43: Rebel attack on El Cobre, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 113)
        These frames show a small-unit, fast-moving rebel attack on El Cobre (see also Print 42.) Frames 11-23 show Capt. Rigoberto Ramirez planning night attack and scanning El Cobre valley from overlooking hilltop. Frames 6-16: rebel unit prepares for attack. Rest of frames are night shots of attack target - army supply huts outside El Cobre burning after rebel strike.
      - Book II Print 44: Rebel attack on El Cobre, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 114)
        These frames show a small-unit, fast-moving rebel attack on El Cobre. This is Capt. Rigoberto Ramirez's platoon.
      - Book II Print 45: Capt. Rigoberto Ramirez's rebel troops, undated (Box 2, Folder 115)
        Capt. Rigoberto Ramirez's rebel troop on march above Puerto Boniato. Capt. Ramirez shown in frames 28-29. Note that sound of approaching vehicle brings rebels into ambush positions shown on frames 30-37 (vehicle turned out to be captured rebel jeep.)
      - Book II Print 46: Rebel military breakthrough into Las Minas de Bueycito, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 116)
        These photos, shot in early fall of 1958, document decisive rebel military breakthrough in its initial stage: all around the Sierra Maestra range government forces are withdrawing, evacuating small, hard-to-defend outposts and minor towns. This sheet shows the taking of a small town, Las Minas de Bueycito, by forces from Cdte. Fidel Castro's own Columna Nr. Uno: it was a momentous event, for it was the first real town occupied (if only for twenty-four hours) by this column. Cdte. Humberto Sorí Marin, rebel's Judge Advocate General and the commander who led this particular advance, is shown on horseback on Frame 24. Capt. Mario Vasquez, another senior troop leader, is shown on frame 30. Woman - the local pharmacist - detained for questioning on charges that she was a government informer (not an implausible idea, for this town had just been evacuated after long occupation by a government battaillon) shown in frames 5-9.
      - Book II Print 47: Rebel military breakthrough into Las Minas de Bueycito, undated (Box 2, Folder 117)
        This sheet shows rebel entry into Las Minas de Bueycito, first town to be seized and held for twenty-four hours by troops of Cdte. Castro's own Columna Nro. Uno (see also Print 46.) Fidel Castro is shown on frames 19-20: this was a historical occasion, for he had entered Las Minas at nightfall on horseback, and is shown here in local general store back room (a store belonging to the pro-rebel Abich family repeatedly mentioned by Che Guevera) talking to town leaders. However, since everyone was terrified of appearing in any sort of published photographic account of this event - that is, a published account that would document collaboration or sympathy with the rebels after the army troops had returned in strength a few days later, an event anticipated by all - picture taking was limited that night. It was restricted to some shots of Paco Cabrera, one of Columna Uno's senior troop leaders, drinking beer (frame 6); other men from the column having a bang-up dinner; a shot of Fidel's faithful cook (frame 21); and shots of rebels withdrawing early next morning (frames 21-28).
      - Book II Print 48: Headquarters of Fidel Castro's Columna Uno, outside of Las Minas de Bueycito, undated (Box 2, Folder 118)
        This sheet shows the headquarters unit of Fidel Castro's Columna Uno operating just outside Las Minas de Bueycito (see also Print 47.) Frame 13 et seq.: Fidel's mayordomo-cook, Emilio Moran. Frames 26-37 show significant event: influx of recruits from surrounding areas. With government forces showing unmistakable signs of weakness, rebel recruiting rose rapidly. These recruits had already undergone some staging and selection at a rebel induction station; they are here on their way for combat training at one of the several such facilities acquired by guerrilla forces by early fall of 1958. Frames 23-25 show rebel recruits with a cherished (presumably captured) military pistol. Photographer (St. George) is shown on frame 16.
      - Book II Print 49: Castro headquarters at La Plata, undated (Box 2, Folder 119)
        Frames 15-29 show Fidel giving TV sound interview to CBC cameraman Erik Durschmied. Frames 11-13 show the headquarters dentist at La Plata station, Dr. Enrique Borges, working on teeth of Celia Sanchez. Other frames show two rebel personalities: Capt. Mario Hidalgo (frames 6-8) and young United States recruit to rebel forces, name unknown (frames 3-5.) See also Prints 33 and 34.
      - Book II Print 50: Carretera Central, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 120)
        The carretera central below Puerto Boniato shows ample evidence by the fall of 1958 of effective rebel interdiction of highway traffic. Buses and trucks shown here have all been blown up or burned by rebel highway patrols, the so-called bazukeros. Villagers help by emptying crippled truck (frame 14).
      - Book II Print 51: The outpost of Capt. Humberto Diaz Rodriguez, undated (Box 2, Folder 121)
        Capt. Humberto Diaz Rodriguez's outpost and its pork-roast-in-progress (see also print 2).
      - Book II Print 52: Villa of Jose Aleman, undated (Box 2, Folder 122)
        This shows the sumptuous villa of Jose Aleman, Minister of Education in earlier government of President Carlos Prio Socarras: even in that loose establishment, Minister Aleman was an outstanding corruptionist.
      - Book II Print 53: Entertainment displays in Habana, undated (Box 2, Folder 123)
      - Book II Print 54: Andrew St. George with group of peasant boys and armed rebels, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 124)
        This print features images of the photographer, Andrew St. George, sitting with a group of small peasant boys who watch in fascination as he shows them the workings of his camera (fall, 1958). The boys are under the protection of more than one armed rebel and probably reside at the rebel outpost and safehouse pictured in the back of frame 34, top row. See also Print 55.
      - Book II Print 55: Andrew St. George with group of peasant boys and armed rebels, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 125)
        This sheet features images of the photographer, Andrew St. George, as he relaxes with peasant children and rebel soldiers guarding a safehouse and rebel outpost in an isolated rural area at the foot of the Sierra Maestra (fall, 1958). Frames 26-30 depict the group of peasant boys to whom St. George was showing his camera in Print 54. Prints 7 through 22 show St. George riding around in a rebel-driven jeep with camera in hand; it is not clear who is taking pictures of him. See also Print 54.
    - Contact Book III
      - Book III Prints 1-5: Meeting of representatives of the United States and the 26th of July Movement, 1958 July (Box 2, Folder 126-130)
        These prints document the arrival of large number of reporters (Prints 1-2) to the Second Front "Frank País," opened in the spring of 1958 by Raúl Castro and his large number of rebel troops in the area near Banes, Oriente, where the largest number of United States-owned properties were concentrated. The reporters were visiting on the occasion of the first direct negotiations between representatives of the United States government's consular office in Santiago de Cuba and members of the 26th of July Movement. Their meeting, as seen in Prints 3-5, was arranged in response to the seizure of forty-eight hostages, including twenty-eight marines, by Raúl Castro's forces in protest of the United States' continued supplying of Batista's air force with military weaponry, including napalm and other materials. Batista's pilots had flown over one hundred missions in the area, bombing exclusively civilian rather than guerrilla targets as part of a counterinsurgency campaign he called "Total War." Print no. 4 shows the reporters, including CBS newsman Robert Taber (frame 15, hatless man on the left), taking off from the United States naval base at Guantánamo and flying over the area. Print No. 5 shows Vilma Espín (frames 18-20) apparently showing off her shooting skills with an automatic weapon, as well as Raúl Castro (in cowboy hat) with reporters and U.S. consular agents (frames 4-12). See also Prints 6 and 7.
      - Book III Print 6: United States hostages, 1958 July (Box 2, Folder 131)
        This print shows United States hostages held by Raúl Castro's forces in the liberated zone created by his recently opened Second Front "Frank País," preparing to be released. The hostages were taken as part of a defensive strategy developed in June 1958 when evidence emerged that the United States was continuing to ship military supplies (such as napalm) to Batista's air force through Guantánamo Bay Naval Base, despite the fact that the United States had declared an official embargo on further arms shipments in March of that year. In May, Batista's air force flew over one hundred flights that bombed and attacked the civilian population in the mountains that offered aid to the rebels. The hostage (shown shaving in frames 5-7) appears to be one of the United States company employees taken hostage, rather than a marine. The twenty-eight marines captured were being held elsewhere. See also Prints 1-5, 7, and 8.
      - Book III Print 7: United States hostages, 1958 July (Box 2, Folder 132)
        This print shows United States hostages held by Raúl Castro's forces in the liberated zone created by his recently opened Second Front "Frank País," preparing to be released. The hostages were taken as part of a defensive strategy developed in June 1958 when evidence emerged that the United States was continuing to ship military supplies (such as napalm) to Batista's air force through Guantánamo Bay Naval Base, despite the fact that the United States had declared an official embargo on further arms shipments in March of that year. In May, Batista's air force flew over one hundred flights that bombed and attacked the civilian population in the mountains that offered aid to the rebels. The four American men shown in frames 11-20 with their guerrilla captors were being interviewed by visiting foreign reporters. They worked for the nearby United States government-owned Nícaro Nickel Mining Company. See also Prints 1-6 and 8.
      - Book III Print 8: Rebel safe house, United States hostages, 1958 July (Box 2, Folder 133)
        Images of the exterior and interior of a rebel safe house, probably in Raúl Castro's Second Front "Frank País," near Banes, Oriente. In frames 8-16, young girls and rebels are seen gathered around a table, apparently playing cards and drinking bottles of soda pop. St. George took these photographs while covering the capture and release of U.S. hostages by Raúl Castro's forces for Life magazine. See also Prints 1-7.
      - Book III Print 9: First victory speech by Fidel Castro, 1959 January 1 (Box 2, Folder 134)
        Taken on January 1, 1959, and stamped January 7, 1959, on the reverse side, this print documents the first victory speech given by Fidel Castro upon the fall and flight from Cuba of the dictator Fulgencio Batista. Having taken the reins of power in the city of Santiago de Cuba earlier that day, Fidel declared Santiago the temporary capital of the country and spoke for over three hours, well past midnight, to a huge crowd gathered in the city's central plaza. Among the dignitaries who lent support on that day was the Archbishop of Santiago de Cuba, Enrique Pérez Serante (frames 9-10). To the right of Fidel Castro in frames 33-36 (wearing glasses, bearded) is the longtime rebel underground leader for Manzanillo, Felipe Guerra Matos. See also Prints 20, 22, 31, 32, 39 and 41.
      - Book III Print 10: Civilian dwellings destroyed by bombings by Batista air force, [1959 January 1, 2?] (Box 2, Folder 135)
        This print shows the destruction of civilian dwellings by Batista's air force bombing campaign in the weeks leading up to the final collapse and partial surrender of the dictator's high command. Frames 11-12 show a Catholic priest, probably a Franciscan, speaking with members of the rebel forces in an area that appears to be an abandoned bunker. In many cases, Batista's troops gave themselves up to the conquering rebels through Catholic clerics who served as intermediaries. See also Print 12.
      - Book III Print 11: Fidel Castro taking over military base, 1959 January (Box 2, Folder 136)
        Fidel Castro and troops taking over a Cuban military air base, probably located in Oriente, and commandeering a military tank. Herbert Matthews of the New York Times can be seen in suit and tie standing behind Fidel Castro in frame 4 of this print. Matthews met Fidel at the air base in the first days following the rebel victory. He had not seen Fidel since their first encounter in the mountains on February 17, 1959. See also Print 12.
      - Book III Print 12: Damage to civilian housing by bombing of Batista's air force; rebels riding tank, 1959 January (Box 2, Folder 137)
        Contains two prints. The first print shows damages caused to civilian housing by Batista's air force bombing raids during the last weeks of 1958 before the collapse of the regime. The second print shows rebels riding on a tank followed by the jeep in which the photographer was riding. It is likely that these images were taken in the first or second day following the rebel victory when St. George and two other journalists, Jules Dubois of the Chicago Tribune and Jay Mallin of Time-Life, accompanied Fidel Castro's caravan from Oriente to Havana.
      - Book III Print 13: Fidel Castro's victory caravan to Havana, 1959 January (Box 2, Folder 138)
        This is the first print that traces Fidel's victory caravan as it made its way to Havana. At various points, Fidel made up for time lost on the way to greet cheering and grateful citizens by taking a British helicopter for portions of the route that his forces had captured from the defeated Batista military days earlier. Here Fidel rendezvouses with members of his team that have advanced by car. Frames 5-12 show some of the guerrillas having breakfast in a workers' cafeteria. See also Prints 14-17 and 47.
      - Book III Print 14: Fidel Castro's victory caravan to Havana; Castro with Eloy Gutiérrez Menoyo, 1959 January (Box 2, Folder 139)
        Taken in the very first days following the collapse of the dictatorship and the rebels' seizure of power, this print shows Fidel being crowded by guerrillas and well-wishers as he proceeds in his victory caravan to Havana. Frames 13-27 show Fidel in profile as he converses with Eloy Gutiérrez Menoyo, a key figure in the military front of El Escambray mountains in the central province of Santa Clara. Gutiérrez Menoyo's early involvement in the urban struggle against Batista was marked by the death of his brother at the hands of Batista's police. Gutiérrez Menoyo later turned against Fidel when the Revolution became Marxist and conspired in a new armed movement against the government until he was captured and imprisoned, ultimately serving twenty years.
      - Book III Print 15: Fidel Castro's seizure of Batista's air force military base, 1959 January (Box 2, Folder 140)
        Taken in the very first days following the collapse of the dictatorship and the rebels' seizure of power, this print shows Fidel Castro and his forces as they take over a military air base once held by Batista's air force. Standing with Fidel in frames 8-22 are a group of former batistiano pilots responsible for the bombing campaign that killed and terrorized so many civilians from May to December 1958. On the occasion of the meeting, Fidel famously assured the men that they would not be subject to trial and execution for their crimes, although he reversed that position several weeks later and all the pilots were executed. Frames 24-25 show two exhausted guerrillas asleep in the back of an American-made car with the driver (frame 26) looking on. See also Print 21.
      - Book III Print 16: Fidel Castro's victory caravan to Havana, 1959 January (Box 2, Folder 141)
        Images documenting the victory caravan of Fidel Castro and his guerrillas as it made its way along Cuba's national highway from Oriente to Havana in the first week of January 1959. Here Fidel Castro is seen standing between vehicles in the center of the highway, talking to his forces, as well as passersby.
      - Book III Print 17: Rebel takeover of military barracks, 1959 January (Box 2, Folder 142)
        This print features various scenes from the rebel takeover of a military barracks or cuartel, probably in Oriente province. Frames 8-17 show a white-robed priest wearing a large cross around his neck talking before a large tank, with the military installation in the back. Prints 5-7 show a small boy-turned-guerrilla who guards recently acquired munitions from the cuartel with a rifle across his lap. The guerrillas incorporated a number of children in the last months before the triumph, especially as Batista's bombing raids left many peasant families homeless and children orphaned. Frames 19-22 show a man behind bars although it is not clear if he is a political prisoner about to be freed or an official that the rebels have jailed. See also Print 45.
      - Book III Print 18: Fidel Castro and Manuel Urrutia, 1959 January 2 (Box 2, Folder 143)